Good morning everybody. Today is דף ק"ט. Daf Kof Tet. We're a
little behind in ק"ח עמוד ב'. Kof Chet Amud Bet. We're in
the middle of dealing with the נח Noach גמרות Gemaras because we're
dealing with the דור המבול Dor HaMabul and we have the first
wide line of
the widest line of ק"ח עמוד ב'. Kof Chet Amud Bet. מכל
הבהמה הטהורה תקח לך שבעה שבעה איש ואשתו. Mi-kol ha-behemah ha-tehorah tikach
lekha shiv'ah shiv'ah ish ve-ishto. איש ואשתו לבהמה מי איתי? Ish ve-ishto
le-behemah mi itei? What do you mean man and wife? You gotta
admit that's a pretty funny פסוק. pasuk. Okay, what do you mean
husband and wife? Since when do בהמות behemot have marriages? So אמר
רבי שמואל בר נחמני אמר רבי יונתן מאותם שלא נעבדה בהם עבירה.
Amar Rabi Shmuel bar Nachmani Amar Rabi Yonatan: me-otam she-lo ne-evdah bahem
averah. Okay,
it doesn't mean that they're married, it means that they are there's
a sense of like fidelity and that they did not go ahead
and have interspecies copulation. מנא ידע? Mi-na yada? And how was נח
Noach supposed to know that? אמר רב חסדא שהעבירו לפני התיבה. Amar
Rav Chisda she-he-eviru lifnei ha-tevah. He let them walk in front of
the תיבה. tevah. כל שהתיבה קולטתו, Kol she-hatevah koletato, if it was
absorbed by the תיבה, tevah, you know I don't remember what that
means if it was like a beam that drew them in or
they tried to go in and those that the תיבה tevah let
in, בידוע שלא נעבדה בהם עבירה, beyadu'a she-lo ne-evdah bahem averah, their
עבירה averah was not done to them. וכל שאין התיבה קולטתו בידוע
שנעבדה בהם עבירה. Ve-kol she-ein ha-tevah koletato beyadu'a she-ne-evdah bahem averah. And
if it would not be taken in, then it was known that
it had had an עבירה averah done to it. Okay, had indeed
this interspecies copulation. רבי אבהו אומר מאותם הבאים מאליהן. Rabi Abahu omer
me-otam ha-ba-im me-eleihen. No, the animals just came on their own accord.
Okay, so God had them come to נח Noach because it says
בא אל נח bo el Noach if you look at the פסוק.
pasuk. It says the animals came to נח. Noach. All right, so
that's an interesting question whether he had to do it or they
just came. עשה לך תיבת עצי גפר. Aseh lekha tevat atzei gofer.
Make for yourself an ark of גפר gofer wood. מאי גפר? Mai
gofer? What's גפר? gofer? אמר רב אדא אמר דבי רבי שילה זו
מבליגא. Amar Rav Adda Amar de-bei Rabi Shila: zu mavliga.
Oh, it's this thing called מבליגא, mavliga, some type of a wood.
ואמרי לה גולמיש. Ve-amrei lah gulmish. And others say it's a different
word called גולמיש. gulmish. So now you know. Is it from the
cedar family? The גולמיש gulmish or the first one? Both of them
are from the cedar family. Okay. צהר תעשה לתיבה. Tzohar ta'aseh la-tevah.
Make a light for the תיבה. tevah. אמר רבי יוחנן אמר לו
הקדוש ברוך הוא לנח קבע בה אבנים טובות ומרגליות, Amar Rabi Yochanan
amar lo ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu le-Noach: kavo bah avanim tovot u-margaliyot, put
in it beautiful like precious stones, כדי שיהיו מאירות לכם כצהרים, kedei
she-yihyu me'irot lakhem ke-tzohorayim, so apparently I guess the sun comes in
and then it reflects on it and it serves as a way
of spreading the light and it'd be like the noonday, it'll serve
like a substitute sun. Yes, does רש"י Rashi on this צהר tzohar
say this? Yes, right. Some say that it's a window and some
say that it's a precious jewel, right. ואל אמה תכלנה מלמעלה. Ve-el
amah tekhalenah milma'lah.
And have it come to a top to an אמה amah like
a hand's, an arm's breadth at the top. I guess it means
like a slanted roof ending at with an אמה. amah. So דבהכי
הוא דקיימא. de-be-hachi hu de-kaima.
That's just good engineering. That way it'll last. Right? Isn't that the
whole thing about like how to make you know the Romans figured
this out, like if you're making a dam and you make it
like this and the water comes in then it like breaks, but
if you make it like this and the water comes in then
because of the way it exerts the pressure actually the oncoming water
strengthens it. There's something like that. Anyway, so I don't know if
the same is true but if you make the top of it
coming up to like you know at an angle then coming up
to a top it's I think similar engineering. From that's the extent
of my knowledge. Okay, so תחתיים שניים ושלישיים תעשה. tachtiyim sheniyim u-shelishiyim
ta'aseha.
Lower lower level second and third levels you should make. תנא: Tana:
תחתיים לזבל. tachtiyim le-zevel. The lowest level is for the dung, for
the excrement. אמצעיים לבהמה. Emtza'iyim le-behemah. The middle level is for the
animals. ועליונים לאדם. Ve-elyonim le-adam. And the top level for the people.
Okay, which is a lot of space for the for the people,
but maybe it kept on getting narrower. Okay. וישלח את העורב. Va-yishlach
et ha-orev. But also even you know you don't want to be
living at the same space with all the animals. וישלח את העורב.
Va-yishlach et ha-orev. And he sent the raven. אמר ריש לקיש תשובה
נצחית השיב עורב לנח. Amar Resh Lakish: teshuvah nitzachit heshiv orev le-Noach.
We had this before that the תשובה נצחית teshuvah nitzachit that בני
ישראל Bnei Yisrael responded to the נביא, Navi, right, which doesn't necessarily
mean that they were right but it means that they won. Like
or it was like a type of an argument that he couldn't
respond to. What did the raven say? אמר לו רבך שונאני ואתה
שנאתני. Amar lo: rabkha soneini ve-atah snatani. Your master, God, hated me
and you hated me. רבך שונאני, Rabkha sonani, מן הטהורים שבעה מן
הטמאים שנים. min ha-tehorim shiv'ah min ha-tmeiyim shenayim. He only asked to
only two of my species are taken onto the תיבה tevah and
the other and the kosher animals seven. ואתה שנאתני, Ve-atah snatani, you
hate me, שאתה מניח מין שבעה, she-atah mani'ach min she-shiv'ah, you could
have taken from the species that has seven, so if one something
happens to the bird there would have been six left, ושלח ממין
שנים, u-shelach mi-min shenayim, and you're taking from the species that there
are only two of. So if something happens to me what's going
to be left of the ravens in the world? אם פוגע בי
שר חמה או שר צינה, Im pogea bi sar chama o sar
tzina, if the you know the angel or whatever of heat or
of cold of something
encounters me, לא נמצא עולם חסר בריה אחת? lo nimtza olam chasar
briyah achat? Then the world will be lacking ravens. It's a good
it's a pretty darn good argument. You should send something from the
species that has seven. או שמא לאשתי אתה צריך? O shema le-ishti
atah tzarikh? Oh, maybe you want maybe your eyes on my wife?
That's got to be one of the funniest lines. אמר לו רשע!
Amar lo: rasha! So נח Noach said to him: wicked! Person, wicked
beast. במותר לך נאסר, B'mutar lach ne'esar, it's
forbidden to me to have intercourse even with people, even with those
that are permitted to me, even with my own wife while we're
on the תיבה. teivah. ובנאסר לי לא כל שכן? u'v'ne'esar li lo
kol shekein? Certainly, you know, an animal, which is the whole reason
that the world was destroyed because of this inter-species copulation, certainly I
would not, I would not do that. Of course, he answered the
last point which was the silly point and not the earlier point
which was the stronger argument. Anyway, ומהיכן נאסרו? u'mei'heichan ne'asru? Now how
do we know that Noah was forbidden to have intercourse on the
ark?
דכתיב, dichsiv, ובאת אל התיבה אתה ובניך ואשתך ונשי בניך אתך, u'vasa
el hateivah atah u'vanecha v'ishtecha u'nshei vanecha itacha, you and your sons
and your wife and your sons' wives. And just to show you
that that's meaningful, דכתיב, dichsiv, it says when they leave, צא מן
התיבה אתה ואשתך ובניך ונשי בניך אתך. tzei min hateivah atah v'ishtecha
u'vanecha u'nshei vanecha itacha. It actually says you and your wife and
your sons and their wives. So it's actually quite a, you know,
stark, the, noticeable, that difference. So you see that they remained separate
on the ark and they only came together, husband and wife, after
they left. ואמר רבי יוחנן, v'amar Rabbi Yochanan, and said Rabbi Yochanan,
מכאן אמרו שנאסרו בתשמיש המיטה. mikan amru she'neasru b'tashmish hamitah. From here
you can infer that they were forbidden to have intercourse on the
ark.
תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, שלושה שימשו בתיבה. shlosha shimshu b'teivah. Three broke
this rule and had intercourse on the ark, וכולם לקו, v'chulam laku,
and they all were punished. Okay, כלב ועורב וחם. kelev v'oreiv v'Cham.
Okay, the dog, the raven, and Ham. Okay,
כלב נקשר. kelev nikshar. So the dog now its fate is that
it's always on a leash.
עורב רק. oreiv rak. The raven spits. I don't know, רש"י Rashi
says it means that that's how it copulates by spitting into the
mouth of the female raven. I somehow, I tend to not believe
that. And why is this a קללה? klalah? It's a disgusting thing.
I don't know. Okay, וחם, v'Cham, and Ham, לקה בעורו. laka b'oro.
He was smitten by his skin, meaning the assumption that Ham or
certainly כנען, Cna'an, his grandson, or whatever, anyway became of dark skin.
You know, so that's never made explicit in the פסוק, pasuk, but
that's obviously a long-held, you know, sort of belief, you know, that
that's sort of the origin of the different colored skins of humanity.
Yeah, but then it says לקה laka though, which sounds like it's
a bad thing. I know it sounds like it's a bad thing.
I'm trying to be a little sensitive. Okay, but yes, it's obviously
understood as a bad thing, right? That's the classic, you know, like
whatever, prejudicial, like myth of like, oh, black people, they were, you
know, they're all cursed because their skin was cursed because they're descendants
of Ham. Yeah. Did you hear the raven speaking? You said the
only other time you said the raven's asked that... Oh, I don't
know, well, we're going to have the יונה yonah speaking. It's enough
with animals speaking. I know, we're going to have the יונה, yonah,
whatever. Yeah, I don't know if
the גמרא Gemara is literally imagining this or putting its words in
the raven's mouth. Yeah, it makes possibly an answer why Noah sent
the עורב, oreiv, because it was בתשמיש המיטה, b'tashmish hamitah, so sort
of, I mean... Maybe. Could be. That it's being punished by like,
alright, well, there's more of you anyway because... Right. רש"י Rashi says
exactly, excuse me, not כנען, Cna'an, I knew there was a mistake,
רש"י Rashi says by חם, Cham, he says שיצא ממנו כוש, sheyatza
mimenu Kush, right? Which is like the Ethiopians and whatever, right? So
the sort of the explanation of the dark skin, of why people
are, why some people are dark skinned. Okay, so understand why Noah
then sent the עורב. oreiv. All right, that's תשובה נצחת. tshuvah nitzachas.
All right, I don't know either. I don't know. Okay. וישלח את
היונה מאתו. vayishlach es hayonah me'ito.
He sent forth the dove. לראות הקלו המים, liros hakalu hamayim, to
see if the waters abated. אמר רבי ירמיה, amar Rabbi Yirmiyahu, מכאן
שדירתן של עופות טהורים עם הצדיקים. mikan shedirasan shel ofos tehorim im
hatzadikim. Why did it say מאתו? me'ito? Why didn't it say וישלח
את היונה? vayishlach es hayonah? What does it mean "from with him"?
So it shows that they like to hang out together, the righteous
and the, and the, what do you call it, and the kosher
birds like to hang out together. Don't ask me. והנה עלה זית
טרף בפיה. v'hinei aleih zayis taraf b'fiha. Behold,
a leaf of an olive tree was torn in its mouth. So
it's going to sort of do a little דרשה drasha here on
the word
בפיה b'fiha to mean that it spoke, and טרף taraf as the
word טרף, teref, a food. Okay, and here's what the דרשה drasha
is going to be. It's not exactly clear what's motivating them precisely
in the פסוקים, psukim, what's the trigger. אמר רבי אלעזר, amar Rabbi
Elazar, אמרה יונה לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא. amrah yonah lifnei haKadosh Baruch
Hu. The dove said to God, ריבונו של עולם, Ribono Shel Olam,
master of the universe, יהיו מזונותיי מרורין כזית, yihyu mezonosai merurin k'zayis,
I would prefer that my,
you know, my food, my sustenance be as bitter as an olive,
ומסורין בידך, umasurin b'yadcha, and be dependent on You, that I would
sort of, you know, fly around and sort of provide for, you
know, through what You provide for me, ואל יהיו מתוקין כדבש, v'al
yihyu metukin k'dvash, rather than be sweet as honey, ומסורין ביד בשר
ודם, umasurin b'yad basar v'dam, and be dependent on people. Like, I
guess he doesn't want to be like some domesticated chicken and being
fed by the farmer, you know, I'd rather fly around
and You God are the one who provides for me. So that's
עלה זית, aleih zayis, you know, as bitter as an olive, טרף,
taraf, טרף, teref, should be the food בפיה b'fiha in its mouth.
Yes? The dove is like the Jewish people, no? Oh, that's interesting,
seeing that as a metaphor for the Jewish people that
we oh that's a very good דרשה. drasha. יישר
כוח. yasher koach. יישר כוח. yasher koach. No, you're right. That's excellent.
I was trying to think like you know what was the point.
I was thinking the point was more like in general like you
know as we we should try to you know we shouldn't be
as dependent on other people. But I think you're much more correct.
It's sort of talking about the fate of the Jewish people. You
know that okay we have it hard in this world but we
feel we believe you know we feel there's a direct connection to
God and sort of that's a preferable fate. Yes. What is your
take on how a man is supposed to get this עלי זית
alei zayis in the whole like... I am not... we're not going
to be discussing now our readings of פרשת נח. parshas noach. We're
just going to do the גמרא. gemara. Sorry. Okay. Okay, מאי משמע
דהאי טרף לשנא דמזוני הוא? mai mashma de-hai taraf lishna de-mezoni hu?
Where do you know this word טרף taraf means food? דכתיב הטריפני
לחם חוקי. de-chtiv hatrifeni lechem chuki. Provide for me the you know
the bread of my sustenance or whatever my you know of the
law. למשפחותיהם יצאו מן התיבה. le-mishpichoseihem yatze'u min ha-teivah. They came out
to their families. אמר רבי יוחנן, amar rabbi yochanan, במשפחותם bi-mishpichosam by
their families ולא הם ve-lo hem but not them. Nobody knows what
that means. The מהרש"א maharsha gives some explanation like nobody knows exactly
how to parse what that means. Maybe it means that now they're
permitted to have intercourse but how does that read in? I don't
know. Anyway, does your footnote in English say anything profound? Well it
says here I mean they were by the families not by themselves.
Oh so they they came out in groups. They didn't come out
individually. Okay, אמר רב חנא בר ביזנא אמר
ליה אליעזר לשם רבא. amar rav chana bar bizna amar lei eliezer
le-shem rabba. So אליעזר, eliezer, he's going to be a figure now
that's going to be in a couple of these stories. He said
to שם shem the elder, נח's noach son,
הכתיב למשפחותיהם יצאו מן התיבה, ha-ksiv le-mishpichoseihem yatze'u min ha-teivah, אתון היכי
עבידיתון? atun heichi avisun? So how were you? I don't exactly get
why it's triggered what the relevance of this פסוק pasuk is because
he's going to ask like what was life on the תיבה, teivah,
you know what was it like for you? Anyway, אמר ליה צער
גדול היה לנו בתיבה. amar lei tzar gadol haya lanu ba-teivah. Oh
it was so hard.
בריה שדרכה להאכילה ביום האכלנוה ביום שדרכה להאכילה
בלילה האכלנוה בלילה. birya she-darkah le-ha'achilah ba-yom he'echelanu ba-yom pi darkah le-ha'achilah
ba-laylah he'echelanu ba-laylah. We had it was 24 hours around the clock.
The day animals we fed at the day, the night animals we
fed at the night. האי זקצא לא הוה ידע אבא מאי אכל.
hai ziksa lo hava yada abba mai achal. There was this chameleon,
father didn't know what it ate. חד יומא הוה יתיב ופלי רמונא.
chad yoma hava yaseiv ve-pali rimona. One day he was there and
chopping up a pomegranates. Good image like seeing נח noach just chop
up the pomegranate. נפל תולעא מיניה ואכלה. nafal tola mina ve-achlah. And
a worm came out of a pomegranate and it ate it. מכאן
ואילך mi-kan va-eilach from that point on הוה גביל ליה חזרא. hava
gaval lei chizra. He would sort of make for him some type
of a I don't know the porridge or something whatever it says.
Knead for him some type of a what it say חזרא chizra
is. Anyway, חזרא. chizra. Anybody know? כי מתלע. ki matla. Anyway, when
this he made for him some type of a thing like a
porridge or whatever and when it got wormy אכלה achlah he would
eat it. Okay, אריה arya now a lion אשתא זינתיה. ishata zinsei.
He was now how do you feed a lion? What you gotta
do? Feed it an animal every day? What's going to be with
the other animals? אריה גביל חזרא? arya gaval chizra? So well there
you go, but not while they're on the תיבה. teivah. He needed
bran. Is that what the urine... bran, yeah the word bran. Whatever,
some type of a porridge or whatever it was. Okay, אריה, arya,
now a lion, אשתא זינתיה. ishata zinsei. So the way he dealt
with the lion was God made it that the lion had a
fever and because the lion had a fever he wasn't hungry for
the entire year.
Okay. So דאמר רב לא בציר משיתא ולא טפי מתריסר זינא אשתא.
de-amar rav lo batzir mi-shita ve-lo tfei mi-tvei sarsar zina ishata. No
less than six and no more than twelve will a fever sustain
a person or like feed a person literally. So presumably maybe it
means twelve months because they were on the ark for twelve months.
Anyway, אורשינה, orchina, now this אורשינה orchina which is some I don't
know what this
אורשינה orchina is... a bird...
some type of a bird... known for longevity. Okay, alright, I think
they say it's a phoenix. A phoenix or
something. אשכחיה אבא דגני בסיפנא דתיבותא. ashkenia abba de-gani bi-sipna de-teivusa. Father
found it sleeping like you know in some of like the you
know some some some side of the ark. אמר ליה לא בעית
מזוני? amar lei lo ba'at me-zoney? Don't you need food? אמר ליה
חזיתיך דהוית טריד. amar lei chazisach de-hava trida. Yeah but I saw
you that you were so busy with all the other animals. אמינא
לא אטרחך. amina lo atzrachach. You know what, I'm not going to
bother you. I'll manage. אמר ליה יהא רעוא דלא תמות. amar lei
yehei ra'ava de-lo samus. May it be God's will that you don't
die. So this is like the story about how this the phoenix
never dies or I guess you
know through whatever. שנאמר ואומר עם קני אגוע וכחול ארבה ימים. she-ne'emar
va-omar im kini egva ve-cha-chol arbeh yamim. And like the sand will
I increase days. So I don't know, somehow that's a verse in
איוב iyov about this phoenix. אמר רב חנא בר ליואי אמר שם
רב לאליעזר. amar rav chana bar livai amar shem rav le-eliezer. So
now שם shem said to אליעזר, eliezer, כי אתו עליכון מלכי מזרח
ומערב. ki asun aleichon melachim mizrach u-maarav. Now that we're talking you're
asking me what was life by me, let me tell you... let
me ask you you know you've had a lot of interesting experiences
with אברהם. avraham. Tell me when you fought that war with all
the kings of the east and the west,
אתון היכי עבידיתון? atun heichi avisun? How did you do it? How
did you fight against them? So אמר ליה אייתי קדוש ברוך הוא
לאברהם ואותי מימינו. amar lei ayisi kadosh baruch hu le-avraham ve-osi mi-yimino.
Okay, and then אברם Avram sit by his right, והוי שדינן vahavei
shadinan and the two of them would throw עפרא afra dirt on
these, you know, kings and their armies, והוי חרבי vahavei charvei and
it would turn into swords, גילא gila and they would throw chaff,
והוי גירי vahavei girei and it would turn into arrows, שנאמר she'ne'emar
מזמור לדוד נאם ה' לאדני שב לימיני Mizmor L'David Ne'um Hashem L'Adoni
Shev Limini
sit by my right hand עד אשית אויביך הדום רגליך ad ashite
oivecha hadom raglecha until I make your enemies your footstool, כתיב ketiv
מי העיר ממזרח Mi he'ir mimizrach
this is like the, this is the פסוק pasuk by ישעיהו Yeshayahu
that we read by the הפטרה Haftorah by לך לך. Lech Lecha.
Who was stirred up from the east? You know, אברם Avram came
from the east to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. צדק יקראו לרגלו Tzedek
yikra'ehu l'raglo righteousness comes by his foot, by his, by you know,
by his step. יתן לפניו גוים Yiten l'fanav goyim he placed nations
in front of him ומלכים ירד u'melachim yard and he has rulership
over kings. יתן כעפר חרבו Yiten ke'afar charbo
his sword is like dust, so the dust turns into swords. כקש
נדף קשתו Kekash nidaf kashto and like chaff his bow, so the
chaff turns into arrows. Okay, now we're going to have a story
that ties this in. נחום Nachum what? Yes. I was thinking about
the animals. I think, I guess this conflicts with the other מדרש,
Midrash, right? That the ארי ari bit נח Noach דאכריה ובעטיה. de'achreih
u'va'leih. Right, exactly. Yep, conflicts.
I guess we're never going to know for sure. נחום איש גם
זו Nachum Ish Gamzu הוה רגיל havei ragil דכל דהוה סריק ליה
dekol d'havei sareik lei אמר גם זו לטובה. amar gam zu letovah.
נחום איש גם זו Nachum Ish Gamzu anything that happened to him
he would say: Oh, this is all for the best. יומא חד
Yoma chad בעו ישראל לשידורי דורון לקיסר. ba'u Yisrael l'shidurei doron l'Keysar.
One day they wanted the Jewish people wanted to send a crowd
to the קיסר... Keysar... Oh, now it's going to be a crown,
now it's a gift, we're going to find out it's a crown.
אמרי Amri בהאי מאי נשדר? behai mai nishdar? Who should we send
it to? You know, I mean it's pretty precious cargo, you know,
who's going to make sure that it gets protected? נשדר בהדי נחום
איש גם זו Nishdar behadei Nachum Ish Gamzu we'll send it through
נחום איש גם זו Nachum Ish Gamzu דמלומד בנסים הוא de'melumad benissim
hu because he's known to have miracles happen to him. Which is
very, you know, interesting, right? They say גם זו לטובה, gam zu
letovah, all the גם זו לטובה gam zu letovah stories are that
the bad things turn out to be good things. So whatever happens
it'll eventually turn out to be good. You know, I've always wondered,
is that really the best lesson for גם זו לטובה? gam zu
letovah? Right? גם זו לטובה gam zu letovah is figuring out how
when the bad stuff remains bad, it's also גם זו לטובה, gam
zu letovah, not because some miracle turns it into something good. But
anyway. Maybe because he had that attitude he was able... Yeah, I
guess. Okay, anyway, so, okay. כי מטו לההוא דיורא Ki matu l'hahu
diyura when he came to an inn, בעו למיבייא ba'u l'mivyat he
wanted to go to sleep. אמרו ליה Amru lei they said to
him: מאי איכא בהדך? mai ika badach? What, what's all the stuff
that you're carrying? אמר להו Amar lehu קא מובלינא כרגא לקיסר. kamo'ivla
karga l'Keysar. Oh, I'm bringing a crown of precious jewels to the
קיסר. Keysar. Like, one also wonders, like,
you know, like he's, he's a little asking for trouble. Anyway, like,
that was a mistake. Exactly. Seriously it is
a tribute.
Oh, I know, okay, right, because it said it was a gift,
but כרגא karga technically, I think, means a crown. But you're right,
in the context it's some type of a gift. Okay. קא
מובלינא... Kamo'ivla... right, because also, like, you don't imagine that just people
give a crown, right? That's something the king sort of gets made.
Anyway,
whatever, okay, I'm bringing a gift to the קיסר. Keysar. קמו בליליא
Kamu b'leilya so they got up at night, שרינו לסיפתיה sharinu l'sifteih
they opened up his luggage, because of course that he, what did
he do with his luggage? He didn't lock it in his room
or something. Okay. ושקלו כל דהוה גביה V'shaklu kol d'havei gabeih and
they took everything that was in his, like, box. Okay. ומלינו עפרא
U'malinu afra and they replaced it with dirt so he shouldn't realize.
כי מטא להתם Ki mata l'hasam so he went on his way,
completely
oblivious. ואשתכח עפרא V'ishtakach afra and he presented it to the קיסר,
Keysar, and the קיסר Keysar opened it up and he saw it
was a box full of dirt. אמר Amar אחוכי קמחייכי בי יהודאי
achuchei k'machaichu bi Yehuda'ei the Jewish people are mocking me. Okay. אפקוהו
למקטליה Afku l'mikteleih they took him out to kill him. אמר Amar
גם זו לטובה. gam zu letovah. Oh, this is all be for
the best. אתא אליהו Ata Eliyahu so אליהו Eliyahu appeared. אדמי להו
Idmi l'hu he appeared to the Romans, כחד מינייהו k'chad minaihu like
one of, one of the Roman officers. אמר להו Amar l'hu you
know, and he said to them: דילמא האי עפרא מעפרא דאברהם אבינו
הוא? dilma hai afra me'afra d'Avraham Avinu hu? You know what? Maybe
this dirt, maybe it's special dirt. Maybe it's the dirt that אברהם
Avraham their father used, their, you know, their
ancestor. I know, I know. What can I tell you? דהוה שדי
עפרא D'hava shadi afra that he would throw the dirt, הוי חרבי
havei charvei and it would turn into swords, גילא gila and he'd
throw chaff, הוי גירי havei girei and it'd turn into arrows. בדקו
ואשתכח הכי Badku v'ishtakach hachi
they tested it and they thought: Oh yeah, this is that magic
dirt. Okay. הוה מחוזא דלא הוה יכלי למיכבשיה. Hava mechuza d'la hava
yachlei l'michbesheh. There was a certain city that they were not able
to conquer until this
point. שדו מההוא עפרא ליה Shadu me'hahu afra lei they threw from
this dirt on it,
וכבשוהו v'chabshu'ei and they conquered it.
עיילוהו לבי גנזי Ailu l'vei ginzei they brought him into the king's
treasure house, נחום Nachum now, now that they saw how powerful this
dirt was. אמרו ליה Amru lei they said to him: שקול דניחא
לך shekol d'nich lach take whatever you want. So מלי לסיפתיה דהבא
mallei l'sifteih dahava he filled
his box with gold. כי הדר אתא Ki hadar ata when he
came back to the inn, אמרו ליה הנך דיורי amru lei hanach
diyurei so the people who lived there said: מאי אמפיתא לבי מלכא?
mai ampeita l'vei malka? They, because presumably he also told them I
have a box full of gold.
So they said: Well, what did you bring to him that you
came back and you were
rewarded? So אמר להו amar lehu he said to them: מאי דשקלי
מהכא אמפיתי להתם. mai d'shakli me'hacha ampeiti l'hasam. Whatever I took from
here is what I brought there. So שקלו אינהו shaklu inhu so
they said: Oh, let's try that, let's
see...
I guess and he didn't tell them the whole story. He just
said I brought what we had here. Reminds me of that old
Wise Men of Chelm story where the
guy from Chelm goes traveling and he goes to this place that
they have gold in the streets and everything and all these precious
jewels, but he tastes the food and it's awful. He realizes what
they don't have is, they don't have
onions to make the food taste better. So he brings in a
wagon full of onions and they can't imagine how good the food
tastes so they pile up his wagon with gold and he takes
his whole wagon back with gold. His friends hears of this and
he says, I can do him better. Like onions, like garlic, that's
really what they need. So he brings a wagon full of garlic
and they say, this is amazing, we're going to give you our
most precious stuff. So he takes back a wagon full of onions.
Anyway,
דור הפלגה אין להם חלק לעולם
הבא. Dor Haflaga ein lahem chelek l'olam haba. The generation of the
dispersion doesn't have a portion in the world to
come. מה עבדו, mai avdu, what did they do wrong? Let's see
how satisfied you are by the Gemara's answer. אמרי דבי רבי שילא,
Amri d'vei Rabbi Shila, from the house of Rabbi Shila they said,
נבנה מגדל ונעלה לרקיע, nivneh migdal vena'aleh l'rakia,
this is the classic answer, they wanted to go up to heaven.
ונכה אותו בקרדומות venakeh oto bekardumot and we'll go ahead and we'll
attack God with axes or kardumot or hammers. כדי שיזובו מימיו. k'dei
sheyazuvu meimav.
Now, because of the whole issue, apparently, it's interesting, we just got
through with the flood but we've constantly had a repeating theme that
the one thing that people are regularly dependent on God for is
rain. It comes from the heavens, you pray for rain, it's uncertain.
So let's just make sure that the guy who's controlling the switch,
like we get control of that switch and we can make sure
that it keeps on raining. That was what was motivating them. מחכו
עלה במערבא, machachu aleh b'ma'arava, in Eretz Yisrael they laughed at this
explanation. אם כן יבנו אחד בטורא. Im ken yivnu echad b'tura.
Why does it say ויסעו בקעה, vayisu bikah, they went to a
valley? Gotta admit that's a pretty darn good question. If they're trying
to get up to heaven you don't build it in a valley.
אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא, Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba, they should
have built it on a mountain. אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא, Amar
Rabbi Yirmiyah bar Abba, אמר רבי ירמיה בר אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah
bar Elazar, נחלקו לשלוש כיתות. necheliku l'shalosh kitot.
There were three different groups, which is interesting because you think part
of the whole thing is that they're all unified, but maybe the
point is you can unify people in one mission, different people have
different motivations. There were three groups. אחת אומרת, Achat omeret, one was
saying, נעלה ונשב שם, na'aleh veneshev sham, let's just go up and
take residence up there, maybe it'll protect us still, but you'd build
it on a mountain then. That's true. The Gemara is not giving
up, talk about קושיא נצחית, kushiya nitzchit,
that point about like you should be building it on a mountain
if you wanted to go up to heaven is a pretty darn
good argument against it, but the Gemara is still working with that
theory that the point was to get up to heaven. It never
answers the question of why build it in a valley. The people
are still trying to get up to heaven. What's in trying to
get up to heaven? There are three opinions. One says let's just
take residence there, maybe they wanted to avoid the next flood or
maybe they wanted to consider themselves god-like creatures but they didn't want
to go to war against God. ואחת אומרת v'achat omeret נעלה ונעבוד
עבודה זרה, na'aleh vena'avod avoda zara,
let's go up and worship idols. Why do you have to go
up to heaven to worship idols is not at all clear to
me. I don't understand the logic behind that one. And if you
say it means to do war against God, well that's the third
one. ואחת אומרת v'achat omeret נעלה ונעשה מלחמה, na'aleh vena'aseh milchama, let's
go up and we'll do war against God. I thought it meant
more literal, we'll take our axes and like chop away at the
sky or something and like try to, I don't know, let's take
a look. זו שאומרת נעלה ונשב שם, Zu she'omeret na'aleh veneshev sham,
the one that just wanted to take residence over there, so that
was a quest, they didn't really want to compete with God, that
was just a question of where they were going to like living
in a better place. So their punishment was הפיצם ה', hepitzam Hashem,
they were scattered. They just didn't get to live together. It was
an issue of where they were living. Also what was like living
up there? According to, you're not divine, you're human. וזו שאומרת נעלה
ונעשה מלחמה, v'zu she'omeret na'aleh vena'aseh milchama,
let's do war. So they wanted to be greater than God, so
they were נעשו קופים ורוחות ושדים ולילין. na'asu kofim veruchot veshedim v'lilin.
They were made into monkeys and spirits and demons and liliths. They
were made subhuman. Their problem was that they wanted to be divine,
so their מידה כנגד מידה midah keneged midah punishment is that they
were made subhuman. Those two I understand. וזו שאומרת נעלה ונעבוד עבודה
זרה, v'zu she'omeret na'aleh vena'avod avoda zara,
let's go worship idols, כי שם בלל ה' שפת כל הארץ. ki
sham balal Hashem sepat kol ha'aretz. There God mixed up all of
their languages. So what does that have to do as a מידה
כנגד מידה midah keneged mi-dah of wanting to worship idols? So Rashi
says, let me just check what Rashi, Rashi, what does
Rashi
say? בלל לשונם כדי שלא יבינו אחד מחבירו לדבר על עבודה זרה,
balal leshonam kedei shelo yavinu echad mechaveiro ledaber al avoda zara, to
prevent them from being, it's not at all satisfying, the מידה כנגד
מידה midah keneged midah isn't satisfying, why they wanted to go up
to heaven to worship עבודה זרה. avoda zara. I think what I
would suggest is that the עבודה זרה avoda zara here is more
Rambam's idea of עבודה זרה avoda zara or like a version of
עבודה זרה avoda zara is not to worship of other gods, but
the worship of intermediaries. So How you want to go up to
heaven because maybe in the heaven maybe God isn't in the heaven
but maybe God's maybe you know higher or whatever but that's where
the sun and the moon are and that's where whatever so you
want to worship some type of intermediaries. But the problem with worshipping
intermediaries is that it corrupts the idea of a God, right? So
therefore God corrupted their language. Right? He made, you know, this became
sort of rather than becoming an easier way to access God, it
became an obstruction, it became a barrier, right? So that's like the
עבודה זרה Avoda Zara idea. So also the language went from the
ease of communication to the inability of communication. That's the best I
could suggest. Okay,
where were we?
You noted that they were turning to creatures, it says that השם
Hashem stripped them of the divine image. Yeah, that was basically my
point. Right? You're right, I was sort of saying subhuman, but the
point is the other way exactly. That's a nice way of saying
it. They wanted, they were made בצלם אלהים B'tzelem Elohim which made
them think that they were actually divine, so actually they lost that
divine aspect of them. That's a nice way of saying it. Okay
so, fine.
תניא, Tanya,
we turn to the ברייתא, Baraita, רבי נתן אומר כולם לשם עבודת
כוכבים נתכוונו. Rabbi Natan omer kulam l'shem Avodat Kochavim nitkavnu. They were
all trying to do עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. כתיב הכא ונעשה לנו
שם וכתיב התם ושם אלהים אחרים לא תזכירו. Ksiv hacha v'na'aseh lanu
shem u'ksiv hatam v'shem Elohim acherim lo tazkiru. מה להלן עבודת כוכבים
אף כאן עבודת כוכבים. Ma lahalan Avodat Kochavim af kan Avodat Kochavim.
And also I could have pointed to
earlier. אז, Az, what would I say? אז Az something, אז הוחל
לקרוא בשם ה'. Az huchal likro b'shem Hashem. Okay, אמר Amar but
that sounds like שם ה', Shem Hashem, so this is clear this
is שם אלהים אחרים. shem Elohim acherim. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi
Yochanan, מגדל שליש נשרף. Migdal shlish nisraf. What happened? So we know
what happened to the people. Where's the tower? Maybe we should go
find the tower. So no, a third of it got burnt, ושליש
נבלע, v'shlish nivla, the bottom third got swallowed up in the ground.
The top third got burnt, ושליש קיים, v'shlish kayam, and the middle
third is still there, you can go see it. אמר רב, Amar
Rav, אויר מגדל משכח. Avir migdal meshake'ach. So if you want to
know, they're trying to explain like why nobody has ever seen this
מגדל. migdal. So his answer is, oh, the air around the tower
makes you forget that you were there. Okay? So everybody who tries
to see it, you leave, you can't remember where it was. So
it's implied that you were up to the altitude? Oh, maybe. Or
it's sort of like that Wonder Woman movie, right? Which the island
was like protected so nobody anyway, whatever. I wonder what the גמרא
Gemara would think about our skyscrapers today. Yeah, exactly, heaven, trying to
live there. Exactly. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't say there's an intrinsic
problem with making high buildings, you know? It's trying to figure out
what the sin was, because there isn't an intrinsic problem making high
buildings. Okay. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, בבל ובורסיף. Bavel u'Borsif.
So this was made in בבל, Bavel, right, בארץ שנער. b'Eretz Shinar.
And בורסיף Borsif is apparently also some place in that region. So
those two places סימן רע לתורה. siman ra l'Torah. They're bad signs
of the Torah because since they have the tower there and the
tower caused the people to forget that they saw it, so you
know somehow that's like in general which is pretty ironic since they
were in בבל. Bavel. Okay. Anyway, סימן רע לתורה. siman ra l'Torah.
מאי
בורסיף? Mai Borsif? אמר רב אסי בור שאפי, Amar Rav Assi Bor
Shapi, a well that draws, I think רש"י Rashi says that it
draws out the תורה Torah or something or that it draws what
does רש"י Rashi say?
Yeah, yeah, draws out, like yeah, like pulls out the memory or
something like that. I don't know. אנשי סדום אין להם חלק לעולם
הבא. Anshei Sedom ein lahem chelek l'Olam HaBa. Now moving from, so
we did דור המבול, Dor HaMabul, דור הפלגה, Dor HaPlaga, now דור
סדום. Dor Sedom. I should say by the way that the גמרא
Gemara completely, or at least so far that I've seen, does not
really get into the significance of why some people don't have, aren't
עומדין בדין. omdin b'din. Right? The משנה Mishna made all these distinctions:
Are you or are you not עומדין בדין? omdin b'din? Are you
yes עומדין בדין omdin b'din but you don't get עולם הבא? Olam
HaBa? So the גמרא Gemara sort of had a פסוק, pasuk, right,
לא ידון רוחי לא דין ולא רוח, lo yadon ruchi lo din
v'lo ruach, but it never bothers to explain like what the logic
is behind the hierarchy, what the significance is of עומדין בדין omdin
b'din and why some people get it and some don't. Okay, but
now we move on to סדום. Sedom. אנשי סדום רעים וחטאים אין
להם חלק לעולם הבא. Anshei Sedom ra'im v'chata'im ein lahem chelek l'Olam
HaBa. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. אנשי סדום אין להם חלק לעולם הבא,
Anshei Sedom ein lahem chelek l'Olam HaBa, שנאמר ואנשי סדום רעים וחטאים
לה' מאד. she'ne'emar v'Anshei Sedom ra'im v'chata'im l'Hashem me'od. רעים בעולם הזה
וחטאים לעולם הבא. Ra'im b'Olam HaZeh v'chata'im l'Olam HaBa. Wicked in this
world, sinners for the world to come. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav
Yehuda, רעים בגופם, ra'im b'gufam, they do other דרשות drashot of the
double language of רע ra and חטאים. chata'im. Evil
and sinners. רעים בגופם Ra'im b'gufam with their bodies, וחטאים בממונם, v'chata'im
b'mamonam, their money. So they didn't provide for the poor and they
did actual sins with their, you know, with their own selves. Okay,
רעים בגופם דכתיב ואיך אעשה הרעה הגדולה הזאת וחטאתי לאלהים ra'im b'gufam
d'ichtiv v'eich e'eseh hara'ah hagedolah hazot v'chatati l'Elohim by יוסף Yosef and
אשת פוטיפר. Eshet Potifar.
So that means here and again we're continuing with the issue of
the theme of sexual sin. Okay, so that means that there were
sins in sexual ways and sexual misconduct.
וחטאים בממונם דכתיב והיה בך
חטא. v'chata'im b'mamonam d'ichtiv v'hayah becha chet. That's if you don't give
to the poor person he'll call out to God and there'll be
a sin, so they didn't provide for the poor.
Which if you think about it were the same two major sins
that the גמרא Gemara identified with דור המבול. Dor HaMabul. Right? At
the end we were emphasizing constantly the sexual sin, השחית כל בשר
hishchit kol basar etc., but earlier it had mentioned חמס chamas and
stealing and so on and that their גזר דין gezar din was
נחתם nechtam over גזל, gezel, right? So these were, you know, desiring
and taking, that was the sort of whole point that I was
making. Anyway, so it's the same two things that are being repeated
here. Okay, so that's רעים וחטאים. ra'im v'chata'im.
Okay,
where were we?
וחטאים לה' מאד וחטאים לה' ויהי בך חטא. V'chata'im l'Hashem me'od v'chata'im
l'Hashem vay'hi b'cha chet. לה', L'Hashem, to God, זו ברכת השם, zu
birchas Hashem, so it wasn't bad enough that it was these like
moral sins, they actually also like religiously like rejected God, they blasphemed.
Okay, מאד, me'od, greatly, שמתכוונים וחוטאים. shemitkavnim v'chotim.
They were doing it not just because of their יצר הרע. yetzer
hara. They did it like they really got into it, which could
mean like they, you know, really did it סתם, stam, like very
intensely, but it could also probably mean a sense of להכעיס l'hachis
seems to be an element here as well, like they were doing
it to spite God. Okay, במתניתא תנא, B'masnisa tana, רעים בממונם וחטאים
בגופם. ra'im bemamonam v'chata'im begufam. It just reverses the meaning of the
words, but it's the same point, their property and their body. רעים
בממונם, Ra'im bemamonam, רעים ra'im means with their property, דכתיב ורעה עינך
באחיך האביון, dichsiv vera'ah enecha be'achicha ha'evyon, your eyes will be bad
against your fellow poor person and you won't
give him. וחטאים בגופם, V'chata'im begufam,
דכתיב וחטאתי לאלוהים, dichsiv vechatasi l'elohim, and I will sin to God,
which is the end of the פסוק pasuk by יוסף. Yosef. So
רעים וחטאים, ra'im v'chata'im, each word can refer to both to support,
you know, with money, support of the poor, or sexual sin. לה',
L'Hashem, okay, זו ברכת השם, zu birchas Hashem, so so far very
similar. מאד, Me'od, זו שפיכות דמים. zu shefichus damim. Not to sort
of make it as they're just doing it to spite God or
whatever, they are doing a religious sin, they're blaspheming God, but also
the great sins is actually murder, שנאמר גם נקי שפך מנשה הרבה
מאד, shene'emar gam naki shafach Menashe harbeh me'od, back to the
מנשה. Menashe. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, אנשי סדום לא נתגאו אלא בשביל
טובה שהשפיע להם הקדוש ברוך הוא. Anshei Sedom lo nisga'u ela bishvil
tovah shehishpia lahem hakadosh baruch hu. This will sound very familiar, סדום,
Sedom, but it's very parallel to the דור המבול, dor hamabul, the
whole thing, the types of sins that they did. It was only
because of all the goodness that God poured out to them. You're
wondering why God didn't realize that that doesn't work. Okay, ומה כתיב
בהם? u'mah ksiv bahem? What does it say by them? So it
was the same way back then, we were quoting פסוקים psukim by
איוב, Iyov, here too, to describe how wonderful they had it. ארץ
ממנה יצא לחם, Eretz mimena yatza lechem, bread came out of the
ground, ותחתיה, vesachteha, by the way, just look at those words, המוציא
לחם מן הארץ. hamotzi lechem min ha'aretz. ארץ ממנה יצא לחם ותחתיה
נהפך כמו אש, Eretz mimena yatza lechem vesachteha nehepach kemo esh, underneath
it also it turned into fire, all right, so there was a
beautiful land, but then, you know, גפרית ואש, gofris va'esh, it turned
into fire. מקום ספיר אבניה ועפרות זהב לו, Makom sapir avaneha ve'afros
zahav lo, where its stones were like
sapphires and it had gold dust. נתיב לא ידעו, Nasiv lo yedau,
but they did not know the right
path. נתיב לא ידעו עיט. nasiv lo yedau ayit. No, excuse me,
the vulture did not know the path. I don't know exactly the
significance of that. ולא שזפתו עין איה, v'lo shezafaso ein ayah, and
the eye of a איה. ayah. What's an איה ayah again? A
vulture, not... It was one of those birds, איה. ayah. Yeah, it's
some prey bird. I know in the English here they say something
different. It was unknown to any robber, unobserved by any spies. Well,
maybe they're reading it metaphorically. Okay, which because, yeah, I mean, it
does mean something like that because it's talking about how wonderful the
land was. Okay, so some type of also raven did not, never
saw it, but
I accept the read of the metaphoric read, right, that no evil
person, like no bandits ever attacked it. לא הדריכוהו בני שחץ לא
עדה עליו שחל, Lo hidrichuhu benei shachatz lo adah alav shachal, and
the sons of a lion did not trample on it and the
similar and also, you know, did not gather on it, the also
lion. So anyway, enemies didn't attack it. Okay, it was an amazing
land. אמרו, Amru, so they said, מכיוון שהארץ ממנה יצא לחם ועפרות
זהב לו, mikeivan sheha'aretz mimena yatza lechem ve'afros zahav lo, since we
have this land that has bread and gold and all this stuff,
למה לנו עוברי דרכים? lama lanu ovrei drachim? Why do we need
passersby? שאין באים אצלנו אלא לחסרנו מממוננו? she'ein ba'im etzlenu ela lachasrenu
m'mamonenu? They're only coming to take all of our wealth from us,
from ממוננו, mamonenu, from anyway... בואו ונשכח
תורת רגל מארצנו, bo'u venishkach toras regel me'artzenu, let's go prevent any
passersby coming into into our land. שנאמר, shene'emar, פרץ נחל מעם גר
הנשכחים מני רגל. peretz nachal me'am gar hanishkachim mini regel. So they
burst forth, I don't get exactly how to read this, they burst
forth the river from the nation that dwells, that made forget from
them the, you know, those of the foot. מני רגל דלו מאנוש
נעו, mini regel dalu me'enosh nau, they they removed themselves from from
like the, you know, from human society, from all the rest of
of humanity. Okay, so the sense we get, basically they prevented people
from passing through their land. Okay,
how do they explain it? I mean they say the same, but
it just seems hard to understand how this פסוק pasuk is... Well,
because it says הנשכחים מני רגל דלו מאנוש נעו, hanishkachim mini regel
dalu me'enosh nau, right? So they made the the the passersby, the
foot, forgotten in their land. Well, what he's saying is that, you
know, that Hashem diverted a stream of fire and brimstone from the
heavenly course, like just like that's the metaphor for a river diverting
it. Oh, to punish those people. Yeah. Oh, so okay. So because
the first half of the verse, פרץ נחל. peretz nachal. So God
diverted this river to punish them, those, a river of fire of
those people who made forgotten from their land. You know, the visitors
and the passersby and so on. Okay, that's a good read. יישר
כח. Shkoyach.
רבא, Rabba, what do you do when the פסוקים psukim quoted in
the גמרא Gemara are harder to parse than the Aramaic? For it's
איוב, Iyov, the problem is איוב. Iyov. Okay, anyway, דרש רבא, darash
Rabba, רבא Rabba explicated, מה דכתיב, mah dechtiv, what's meant by the
verse? עד אנה תהותתו על איש, ad ana tehotetu al ish, how
long will you sort of oppress or something on a person? תרצחו
כולכם, teratzechu chulchem, you will all, you will like, you know, you'll
all commit murder like a leaning wall, כקיר נטוי, kekir natui, גדר
הדחויה, gader hadechuyah, like a pushed over fence or wall. So what
does that mean? I mean,
so מלמד melamed that they would, they would like see the wealthy
people. Now whether it means wealthy people in their land or wealthy
people from elsewhere, anyway, they would obviously be very covetous of the
of the wealthy people's money. ומושיבין אותו אצל קיר נטוי, umoshivin oto
etzel kir natui, and so what they would do is they would
say, "hey, let's go take a walk" and they'd have him sit
right by a wall that was leaning, okay? ודוחין אותו עליו, vedochin
oto alav, they push the wall on him, ובאין ונוטלין את ממונו,
uvain unotlin et mamono, and then they went and they just raided
his property. Okay. דרש רבא, darash Rabba, מה דכתיב, mah dechtiv, so
that goes back to the murder also, right? So because of their
desire and they had it so good, you think they had it
so good they didn't need it, but it just led to not
wanting to share it, to wanting more of it, to being the
self-feeding thing and because of their desire, you know, for more and
more, you know, wealth or whatever, that's led ultimately to murder. Okay.
דרש רבא, darash Rabba, מה דכתיב, mah dechtiv, what's meant by the
verse? חתר בחשך בתים, chatar bachoshech batim,
they dug, you know, with what do you call it, with tunnels
into the homes. יומם
חתמו למו, yomam chatmu lamo,
in the day they had like they they they had like I
don't know, they put a sign on it, they put a sign
on the houses that they would dig into it at the night.
So they dug in in the darkness in the houses that in
the night they had they had put a sign on. We'll see
about that. Seal themselves in. Seal themselves in. I think based on
the next how he's going to explain it, it's kind of more
mean like a חותם chotam is a seal. They had put a
sign on it. Okay. לא ידעו אור, lo yadu or, they did
not know light. Okay, they kept themselves in the dark. מלמד, melamed,
so what would they do? שהיו נותנין עיניהם בבעלי ממון, shehayu notnin
eineihem bebaalei mamon, they saw the wealthy people ומפקידים אצלו אפרסמון, umafkidim
etzelo afarsamon, and they said, "hey, you know what, could you would
you mind keeping some of this precious אפרסמון afarsamon spice in your
house?" they said to this wealthy person. Okay, ומניח אותו בבית גנזיהם,
umaniach oto bevet ginzeihem, and the wealthy person said, "sure, I'd be
happy to do you a
favor", and they went to their homes and they would put this
aromatic fragrance in their, you know, safe, in their storehouse, in their
treasure houses. לערב, le'erev, so that's the sign that they made on
the houses. In the day, they did something that would allow them
in the night to find where they needed to go. Okay, so
that's why I think they're reading it that in the light they
put a sign on it, as it were. לערב, le'erev, in the
evening, באין ומריחין אותו ככלב, ba'in umerichin oto kekelev, they smell it
out like a dog, שנאמר ישובו לערב יהמו ככלב ויסובבו עיר, shenemar
yashuvu la'erev yehemu chekelev viysovvu ir, they will return at night, they
will like search out like a dog,
they will surround the city. Fine. So they smelled it out like
a dog. They knew exactly where the treasure house was now because
they followed the scent. ובאין וחופרין שם, uvain vechotrin sham, and they
dug tunnels there, ונוטלין אותו ממונו, venotlin oto mamono, and that's the
way they were able to steal that money. Okay, so it seems
like I don't know, you would think a treasure house would also
have like good locks on it or whatever, it wouldn't just be
the secret wouldn't just be its location. But anyway, fine. Okay. So
ערום הלכו מבלי לבוש, arom halchu mibli levush, so now what happened
to the person who was wealthy that they now robbed this person
blind? What I'm also not getting is are these the people in
סדום Sedom itself or are these outsiders? Because if the people in
סדום Sedom itself just the whole city keeps on stealing from one
another, it's like it's all just going in a big
circle. Anyway, ערום הלכו, arom halchu, they went naked, the the owners,
מבלי לבוש, mibli levush, ואין כסות בקרה, ve'ein kesus bakarah, without clothes
and they had no clothes
in the cold. חמור יתומים ינהגו, chamor yetomim yinhagu, the the thieves
led away even the donkey of orphans, יחבלו שור אלמנה, yachavlu shor
almanah, they took as collateral the ox of the widow. גבולות ישיגו,
gvulot yasigu, they they moved the boundary lines between property, עדר גזלו
וירעו, eder gazalu vayiru, they stole the flock and they and they
tended them. Okay. והוא לקברות
יובל, vehu likvurot yuval, he will be brought down into the קברות
יובל, kevarot yuval, will be brought brought into the the owner who
was left naked and penniless will be brought brought into the graves,
okay, ועל גדיש ישקוד, ve'al gadish yishkod, and will sort of, I
don't know, dwell by the by the mound or whatever that means.
Okay. דרש רבי יוסי בציפורי, darash Rabbi Yose beTzipori, so רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose explicated this whole story about what they would do in
סדום Sedom and how they would use these tunnels to dig into
the homes with the with the fragrances etc. That's what he gave
this דרשה. drasha. אחתיוהו ליליה אותן תלת מאה מחתרתא בציפורי, achtinehu leilei
otan tlatan ma'ei machtarta beTzipori, so that night 300 people tried it
out and they tried digging tunnels and 300 tunnels were dug to
break into people's homes. homes and ציפורי. Tzipori. Okay, so אתו וקמצערן
ליה atu ve-kamtasre ve-leih they came and they gave him a hard
time. What did you do? You taught all these people this idea
about how to break into the homes? So
אמרו ליה, amru leih, they said to him, יהביתו אורחא לגנבי, yahavitu
orcha le-ganve, you've given a path to for thieves. אמר להו amar
lehu he said to them, מי הוה ידענא דאתו גנבי? mi hava
yadana de-atu ganve? Who I didn't know that thieves would come. It's
the other way, it gets מי הוה ידענא דאתון גנבי. mi hava
yadana de-atun ganve. I didn't realize I was giving my שיעור shiur
to a people that a bunch of thieves. So you know now
of course the funny thing about this whole story is like I
don't understand nobody before ever thought of the idea of digging a
tunnel? So the only new idea here was the perfume. So that
night 300 people gave perfume to people that had storehouses? It's like
what? Like I don't know it doesn't but anyway 300 is of
course an exaggeration altogether. But maybe it means he gave the idea
to a few people. Be careful what you say. Okay anyway. Okay
now moving on. כי נח נפשיה דרבי יוסי, ki nach nafshi de-Rabbi
Yose, now since we're talking about רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose in ציפורי,
Tzipori, so when רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose died שפו מרזיבי דציפורי דמא.
shafu marzeiva de-Tzipori dama. It was so tragic that it was like
the like the you know like the streets of ציפורי, Tzipori, the
water drains, the gutters, were flowing in blood, which is a pretty
graphic and image. So did that mean on the one hand you
could be saying like even though they gave him a hard time
he was still greatly honored or whatever? But also sort of makes
you think we were just talking about murder and theft and whatever
and now you have this image of the blood flowing, so maybe
it's trying to be maybe it's trying to critique the people of
ציפורי, Tzipori, you know? Because these big cities have wealth, right? And
you know it's often true, like you have to imagine that the
גמרא Gemara was also having some critique here of Rome and Roman
society or whatever. Right? So you know these wealthy cities and there's
a lot of crime and so on although the crime usually is
not from the people who are wealthy. Anyway, so the combination of
talking about the גנבים ganavim and then talking about the blood, I
don't know maybe it's a critique of things they saw wrong in
ציפורי. Tzipori. You wanted to say something? Yes I don't know exactly
what I'm mind but there's significance to ציפורי Tzipori's business and its
place in the life of the משנה. Mishnah. Yeah. Yeah I don't
know, it doesn't factor largely in the משנה. Mishnah. רבי יהודה
הנשיא... Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi... Right, I know, but I just don't see
it factoring that much in the rabbinic discourse. You mean you're saying
this is not
blame רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, it's blaming the people. Yeah, well that's
if you especially if you read that his response was I didn't
realize I was giving שיעור shiur to גנבים. ganavim. Okay? Okay. אמרי
דאית ליה תורא מרעי חד יומא דלית ליה מרעי תרי יומא. amri
de-is lei tora marei chad yoma de-leis lei lerei trei yoma. Anybody
who has
a who has an ox has to watch the oxen of the
town one day, you know one day in our rotation. If you
don't have any oxen you have to watch them two days in
our rotation. So of course that's absurd but but you know you
just think that it's mocking them and saying how silly and absurd
they were, but really what it is it's a way of oppressing
the poor. It's like if you think about like you know it's
like when like you know when you have what's it called regressive
taxation or whatever. You know the rich pay less taxes than the
poor, right? So the poor people who don't have any oxen they're
the ones who have to do the watching two days out of
the rotation. ההוא יתמא בר ארמלתא, ha-hu yatma bar almala, so there's
a very you know an orphan the son of a widow, right?
So sort of somebody very you know clearly a person that was
could be abused by this society. הבו ליה תורי למרעי, havu lei
tore le-mirei, they gave him the oxen to watch. אזל שקלינהו azal
shaklinu he took them וקטלינהו ve-katlinu and he killed them all. אמר
להו amar lehu and he said to them, דאית ליה תורא נשקול
חד משכא, de-is lei tora nishkal chad mashka, anybody who came and
owned an ox can come and take one hide, דלית ליה נשקול
תרי משכי, de-leis lei nishkal trei mashkei,
and anybody who didn't own an ox let him take two hides.
Of course there's a problem which is that that's more hides than
there are people whatever. Anyway, אמרו ליה amru lei they said to
him מאי האי, mai hai, what's that nonsense? אמר להו amar lehu
סוף דינא ככתחלת דינא, sof dina ke-techilat dina, what do you mean?
The end is like the beginning. מה תחלת דינא ma techilat dina
the same way the rule you had at the beginning was דאית
ליה תורא מרעי חד יומא דלית ליה תורא מרעי תרי יומא, de-is
lei tora marei chad yoma de-leis lei tora marei trei yoma, that
you know that the one who has watches one day the one
who doesn't watches two, so סוף דינא דאית ליה תורא נשקול חד
דלית ליה תורא נשקול תרי. sof dina de-is lei tora nishkal chad
leis lei tora nishkal trei. Okay,
he bested them, of course one wonders given the nature of the
people of Sodom why they didn't just kill him and get rid
of him. Okay you know like like a real yeah too really
cute smart-aleck boom. All right anyway okay
now דעברי במעברא, da-avrei be-mavra,
similarly they said anybody that passes
by the
you know by the ford by the by the boat or whatever...
the bridge yeah נתיב חד זוזא neisiv chad zuza has to pay
one זוזא zuza as a tax. דלא עברי במעברא, de-la avrei be-mavra,
if you pass over the river in a different way, you do
some other path to get to the other side so we didn't
want to let anybody out of paying the taxes נתיב תרי. neisiv
trei. They'd basically tax you double. Right exactly. So the so the
GW Bridge anybody who passes over pays one everybody else pays double.
Okay anyway so דהוה ליה דרא דלבני, de-hava lei dara de-livni, now
similarly anybody who was like trying to build a you know do
construction and they built a whole they they had a pile of
bricks so So what happened? אתי כל חד וחד שקיל חד. Ati
kol chad vechad shakil chad. Everybody passed by and just treated themselves
to one brick. Big deal, it's just one brick. I'm not really
stealing from you, it's just one brick I'm taking. By the end
of the day, he had no bricks left, right? אמרי אנא חדא
דשקיל, Amrei ana chada deshakeil, I'm just taking one. דהוה שדי תומי
או סומכי, dahavei shadi tumei o samkhei,
somebody who was spreading out garlic or onions to sell. אתי כל
חד וחד שקיל חד. Ati kol chad vechad shakil chad. There's my
garlic and onions. Everybody came and they just helped themselves to one.
אמרי אנא חדא דשקיל, Amrei ana chada deshakeil, I'm just taking one,
I'm not hurting you. And by the end of the day he's
left with nothing. Okay. ארבע דייני הוו בסדום. Arba Dayanei havi biSdom.
Now there were four judges in
Sdom. שקראי, Shakrai, exactly, liar, ושקרוראי, veShakrurai, big liar, זייפי, Zaifi, forger,
ומצלי דינא, uMatzli Dina, and perverter of justice. That was their names,
okay. דמחי ליה לאיתתא
דחבריה, Demachi lei le'itta dechavrei, somebody who smote, who injured his friend's
wife,
ומפלי, umaplei, and hit her and caused injury.
They hear this in ומפלי... umaplei... הפלה, hapala, excuse me, I'm sorry,
הפלה, hapala, right, that works with the rest of the story, I'm
sorry. Right, right, right. Caused her to miscarry, yes, thank you. Right,
yes. אמרי ליה, Amri lei, so they would say to him, הב
ניהלה, havniyalah, give your wife to this guy, הב ניהלה, havniyalah, he'll
get her pregnant and that way he'll restore the fact that he
caused her to miscarry. Okay. דפסקי ליה לאודנא דחמרא דחבריה, Depaskei le'udna
dechamra dechavrei, somebody who cut off an ear of a donkey of
his friend, אמרי ליה הב ניהליה, Amrei lei havniyeih, give him your
donkey עד דקאתיא ad dika'atcha until the ear grows back, but he
gets to use the donkey for the period it takes for the
ear to grow back. דפגעי ליה לחבריה, Depaglei lechavrei, somebody who wounded
his
friend, אמרי ליה הב ליה אגרא דשקל לך דמא, Amri lei hav
lei agra deshakeil lach dama, he wounded you, he caused some blood
to come, that's what I was conflating just with the wife case
with this
case, and so he did you a service, he was a bloodlettor,
so pay him a doctor's
fee, he let some blood for you. Okay. דעבר במברא יהיב ארבע
זוזי, De'avar bemavra yaiv arba zuzei, דעבר במיא יהיב
תמני זוזי. De'avar bemaya yaiv tamni zuzei.
Back to that, the one who passed by through the bridge paid
four, the guy who went to actually not use the bridge and
went through the water he paid eight. זימנא חדא אתא קובאי, Zimna
chada ata kovei, so a certain launderer happened to be passing through.
איקלע להתם, Ikla lehasam, he came. אמרי ליה הב ארבע זוזי, Amri
lei hav arba zuzei, if you came to our town you must
have passed through the bridge, give us four zuz, you must have
passed over the bridge, give us four zuz. אמר להו אנא במיא
עברי, Amar lehu ana bemaya avina, no no no, I didn't use
the bridge, I passed through the water. אמרו ליה אי הכי הב
תמני, Amri lei ifan im kein hav tamni, fine, give us eight
דעבר במיא, de'avar bemaya,
because you passed through the water. לא יהיב, Lo yaiv, and he
refused to give it. פדיוהו, Padyu, they beat him up. אתא לקמיה
דדיינא, Ata lekamei deDayana, he came to the judges. אמרו ליה הב
ליה אגרא דשקל לך דמא. Amrei lei havlei agra deshakeil lach dama.
Okay, so not only do you owe the eight, now you have
to also pay the guy who beat you up because he did
you the service of letting some blood. ותמניא veTamna plus the eight
zuzei דעברת במיא. de'avart bemaya. So now, so that's how perverted and
evil and wicked they are. Now, Eliezer who we had in the
previous Noach story, Eliezer serves as a very convenient figure. He's sort
of he's like the pre-Eliyahu figure, he gets to do he visits
all of these places, okay. So now,
אליעזר עבד אברהם, Eliezer Eved Avraham, איתרמי להתם, itramei hasam, he happened
to go by Sdom veAmora. פדיוהו, Padyuha, they beat him up. אתא
לקמיה דדיינא, Ata lekamei deDayana, he came to the judge. אמר ליה
הב ליה אגרא דשקל לך דמא, Amlei havlei agra deshakeil lach dama,
go pay him the fee, he let this guy beat you up,
let blood. שקל גללא, Shakal iglala, he took גללא iglala which is
either like a stone or like a piece of... גללא iglala often
is dung, but it doesn't fit the context, so Rashi says it
means a stone. He took a
stone, ופדיוהו, upadyuhe, and he banged it on the head of the
judge. יהמיה לדיינא, Yaheimei leDayana, so he used it to hit the
judge. אמר מאי האי, Amar mai hai, the judge says what is
it you're doing? You're beating me up? אמר אגרא דנפיק לי מינך,
Amar agra denafik li minach, now you owe me the payment for
letting blood for you, so that money that you now owe me,
הב ניהליה להאי גברא havniyeih lehai gavra give it to this guy
דחדי בי dechadei bi who beat me up.
להאי, Lehai, וזוזי דידי כדקאי קיימי, ve zuzei didi gakai kaimi, and
I'll just keep my own money.
How do you do? פורייתא. Puraysa. Now they had a bed, this
is the famous מיטת סדום. mittat Sdom. They had a bed דהוו
מגנו עלה אורחי, dehavi magnei alei orchei, that the visitors, travelers would
sleep on. כי מאריך, Ki marich, somebody who was too long, גייזי
ליה, gayezlei, they cut off his legs in order that he would
fit. כי גוץ, Ki gut, if he was too short, מתחלי ליה,
matchilei, they would stretch him until he would fit. Like so that's
the phrase in Hebrew, a מיטת סדום, mittat Sdom, right, somebody exactly
you force you to fit into my structure, exactly, okay. אליעזר עבד
אברהם איקלע להתם, Eliezer Eved Avraham itla lehasam, so Eliezer chanced there.
אמרו ליה, Amrei lei, they said to him, קום גני אפורייתא, kum
ganya apuraya, oh, you're our honored guest, come sleep on our special
guest bed. אמר להו, Amar lehu, he said to them, נדרא נדרית
מיומא דמיתת אימי, nidra nadini miyoma demiset imi, I took an oath
from the time my mother died, דלא גנינא אפורייתא, lo ganya apuraya,
that I refuse to sleep on a bed. All right, so he
got out using honesty. Okay. כי הוה מיתרמי להו עניא, Ki havi
itramei lehu anya, now, when a poor person would come through Sdom,
how they got there we don't know, how they would ever manage
to get in, יהבו ליה כל חדא, yahavlei kol chada, so this
is how they would sort of it wasn't
enough. יהבו ליה כל חד וחד דינרא, yahavu lei kol chad vechad
dinra, everybody would give him a dinar, this poor person, וכתיב שמיה
עליה, ukhtiv shemei alei, and write their name on it. I don't
know how you write the name on a coin, you write the
name on paper money. Anyway, וריפתא לא הוו מזבני ליה. verifta lo
havu mazbeni lei. Then this guy had all this money, but then
everybody refused to sell him food. I don't know why he just
didn't leave with all the money, but they probably because they presumably
didn't let him. כד הוה מיית, kad hava mayit, so then he
died. He died of starvation. So אתו כל חד וחד שקלו דידיה,
atu kol chad vechad shaklu didei, and everybody came back and took
their coins back because they all knew whose coins it was with
the name written on it. So it was really like, oh look
how generous we are, whatever, and of course so, A, they got
to pretend like they were generous, and B, of course, it was
that much more, you know, like,
you know, anguish-filled for the person to have got that money and
not be able to use it. Okay, אתקנו בינייהו, atkinu beinaihu, they
made a condition, כל מאן דמזמין גברא לבי הילולא, kol man demazmin
gavra levei hilula, anybody who invites somebody to a wedding feast,
לישלחו לגלימיה, lishlachu leglimei, will strip him of his clothes if you
invite—the person or the inviter? The inviter, the one who did the
inviting, because they didn't want any, you know, outsiders. הוה ההוא הילולא,
hava hahu hilula, so there was a—there was a wedding feast. איקלע
אליעזר להתם, ikla eliezer lehatam, and Eliezer dropped by there, ולא יהבו
ליה נהמא, velo yahavu lei nahama, they refused to give him bread.
כי בעי למיכל, ki baei lemichal, when he wanted to eat, אזל
אליעזר ויתיב בסופא דכולהו, azal eliezer veyatib besofa dechulehu, so he went
and sat himself down there at the wedding feast. He was a
party crasher. אמר ליה, amar lei, so the guy sitting next to
him said to him, מאן אזימנך להכא, man azminach lehacha, who invited
you here? אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to the guy who
was sitting next to him, את אזימנתין, at azmintan, what do you
mean? You invited me. אמר, amar, so the guy who was sitting
next to him said, דילמא שמעו בי בי דאנא אזימנתין, dilma sham'u
bi bi de'ana azmintan, people will hear this—it's true—but people will hear
him saying this and think I invited him, ולישלחו ליה למאניה מינאי,
velishlachu lei lemanei minai, and they'll strip me naked. שלח גלימיה, shalach
glimei, so he took his cloak, which he didn't want to be
stripped, and רהט לברא, rahat lebara, and ran outside. So then he
went and he moved over one seat and the next guy asked
him the same question and he said the same thing, וכן עביד
לכולהו, vechen avid lechulehu, he did it for every single person sitting
there, עד דנפקו כולהו, ad denafku chulehu, they all ran out, ואכל
איהו לסעודתא, veachal ihu leseudata, and he ate everybody's food. Okay, הוה
ההיא רביתא, hava hahi ravita, there was a certain young woman, דהות
מפקא ריפתא לעניא בחצבא, dehavat mafka rifta le'anya bechatztza, she was the
one צדקת tzadeiket in the town and she would bring out bread
to a poor person hiding it in her jug. Okay, when she
went to draw water. איגלאי מילתא, iglai milta, so it became revealed,
שפיוה דבש, shafyuha devash, they covered her with honey, ואוקמוה על איגרא
דשורא, veokmuha al igra deshura, and they put her on the top
of a wall. אתו זיבורי ואכלוה, atu ziburi veachaluha, the bees came
and consumed her, והיינו דכתיב, vehainu dechtiv, that's what it meant, ויאמר
ה' זעקת סדום ועמורה כי רבה, vayomer Hashem za'akat Sedom va'Amorah ki
rabah,
the outcry of Sedom is great, ואמר רב יהודה על עסקי ריבה,
ve'amar Rav Yehuda al iskei riva, על עסקי ריבה, al iskei riva,
ultimately what sealed their fate was the, you know, was the poignancy
of whatever, the tragedy of what they did to this one good
woman who was trying to save them. Okay, we'll just read—we can
do two more lines quickly. We have one more minute. עדת קרח
אין להם חלק לעולם הבא שנאמר ותכס עליהם הארץ בעולם הזה ויאבדו
מתוך הקהל לעולם הבא, adat Korach ein lahem chelek la'olam haba shene'emar
vatechas aleihem ha'aretz ba'olam hazeh vayovdu mitoch hakahal la'olam haba, in this
world, but the maggid told us about עולם הבא, olam haba, the
next one. עשרת השבטים אין להם חלק לעולם הבא שנאמר וישליכם אל
ארץ אחרת בעולם הזה ויאבדו מתוך הקהל לעולם הבא, aseret hashevatim ein
lahem chelek la'olam haba shene'emar vayashlichem el eretz acheret ba'olam hazeh vayovdu
mitoch hakahal la'olam haba, דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva. רבי אליעזר
אומר עליהם אמר הכתוב ויאמר ה' ה' ממית ומחיה מוריד שאול ויעל,
Rabbi Eliezer omer aleihem amar hakatuv vayomer Hashem Hashem memit umechayeh morid
she'ol vaya'al, God—he brings to death and to life, he brings them
down and brings them up. So presumably you would assume that in
general דור המדבר dor hamidbar would have חלק לעולם הבא. chelek la'olam
haba. תנו רבנן עדת קרח אין להם חלק לעולם הבא שנאמר ותכס
עליהם הארץ בעולם הזה ויאבדו מתוך הקהל לעולם הבא, tanu rabanan adat
Korach ein lahem chelek la'olam haba shene'emar vatechas aleihem ha'aretz ba'olam hazeh
vayovdu mitoch hakahal la'olam haba, דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva. רבי
יהודה בן בתירה אומר הרי הן כאבידה המתבקשת, Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira
omer harei hen ka'aveida hamitbakeshet, they are something like God lost, that
God is still seeking after. Okay, so that's very interesting that even
the עדת קרח, adat Korach, you know, the sense of compassion to
the עדת קרח adat Korach that they were still great people and
God still is, you know, hopes to get them back, שנאמר תעיתי
כשה אובד בקש עבדך
כי מצותיך לא שכחתי, shene'emar ta'iti keseh oved bakesh avdecha ki mitzvotecha
lo shakachti, even they did not forget God's מצוות mitzvot even with
their whole rebellion and ultimately they will—they will be redeemed. Okay, and
then we will start tomorrow with the interpreting the פסוקים psukim about
Korach. All right.